Guide to the E. Richard Hart audio-visual collection 1930-2003
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
E. Richard Hart audio-visual collection
1930-2003
bulk 1982-1990
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0377
Hart, E. Richard
66 audiocassettes, 8 VHS videocassettes, 13 U-matic videocassettes, 1 phonograph record, and 1 compact disc
The E. Richard Hart audio-visual collection (1970-2003) consists of audio and video recordings relating to the history Native Americans and the American West. Hart is an author and researcher associated with the American West Center (Salt Lake City, Utah), the Institute of the American West (Sun Valley, Idaho) and the Institute of the North American West (Seattle, Washington). He has served as an expect witness in several federal court cases involving land claims by the Zuni, some of which are represented in this collection.
Biographical Note
E. Richard Hart is an historian of the American West. He was associated with the American West Center at the University of Utah from 1969 to 1975. From 1979 to 1984, he was director of the Institute of the American West at Sun Valley, Idaho. He was editor for several publications resulting from conferences held by the Institute. In 1984, Hart helped to establish the Institute of the North American West in Seattle, Washington. He has also served as an expect witness in several federal court cases involving land claims by the Zuni Indians.
The E. Richard Hart audio-visual collection (1970-2003) consists largely of audio and video recordings relating to the history Native Americans in the American West, including documentaries, songs and several items pertain to Zuni land claims.
The materials are arranged by format type. Audiocassettes, videocassettes and phonograph records are followed by an addendum of 4 items added in 2002.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the E. Richard Hart papers (Accn 1251) and the Doris Duke Indian oral history project audio recordings (A0001) and transcripts (Ms 417), which were compiled by the American West Center.
Institute of the North American West; Institute of the American West; Duck Valley Indian Reservation (Idaho and Nev.); Zuni Indians--Claims; Zuni Indians--Land tenure; Zuni Indians--History; Social Classes; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Audiocassettes, 1970-1988
  - Indian self-rule: fifty years under the Indian Reorganization Act, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 1-3)
    Produced by Western Media Concepts.
  - American originals, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 4)
    Produced by the National Humanities Center.
  - Westroots 2: agriculture, 1984 September 07; Audiocassette (Cassette 5-6)
  - Walpi 300 years of change, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 7-9)
    Side 1
    Walpi restoration project
    Side 2
    Dr. Fred Eggan, cultural relationship
    Dr. Chuck Adams project
    Side 3
    Dr. Chuck Adams
    Bill Fields, project engineer
    Emery Sekaquaptewa
    Side 4
    Emery Sekaquaptewa (continued)
    Side 5
    Alvin Dashee, Hopi Housing Authority
  - John Gray, 1988 April 05; Audiocassette (Cassette 10)
  - Zuni Tribal Council, 1986 January 22; Audiocassette (Cassette 11-13)
  - Kotuwala:Wa, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 14-16)
  - Tlep to Zuni, 1981 May; Audiocassette (Cassette 17)
  - Zuni Ceremony, 1985 November 11; Audiocassette (Cassette 18)
  - Alex Seowtewa, April 01; Audiocassette (Cassette 19)
  - Notes, 1986 February 13; Audiocassette (Cassette 20)
  - First person radio, 1983 February 10; Audiocassette (Cassette 21)
    KUER radio audition tape
  - Zuni, 1986 October 27; Audiocassette (Cassette 22)
  - Zuni comments, politics, 1985 June 17; Audiocassette (Cassette 23)
  - Zuni SK ceremony, 1985 November 11; Audiocassette (Cassette 24)
  - Wesley Hall, 1981 September 04; Audiocassette (Cassette 25)
  - Dave McKenney: boar dance songs and round range songs, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 26)
  - Great Basin Indians, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 27)
  - Northern Rockies Folk Festival (NRFF) songs, August 06; Audiocassette (Cassette 28)
  - Governor Lewis, 1982 March 16; Audiocassette (Cassette 29-30)
  - Seowtewa, 1970 October 07; 1980 October 08; Audiocassette (Cassette 31-35)
  - Weskema Eriako, Gabriel Pinto, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 36-37)
  - Zuni History Conference, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 38-58)
    Master copies and duplicates.
  - Zuni tapes 1-2, 1984 April 03; Audiocassette (Cassette 59-60)
  - Zuni tapes 3-4, 1984 April 03; Audiocassette (Cassette 61-62)
    Kothliwalawa
  - Zuni statements, 1984 April 03; Audiocassette (Cassette 63-65)
    Tape 1: Statement from religious leaders
    Tape 2: Zuni statements
    Tape 3: Statements
- Videocassettes, 1982-1990
  - Winds of change, 1988 March 09; VHS videocassette (Cassette 1)
  - From stump to stump, 1930; VHS videocassette (Cassette 2)
    A 1930 logging film with transcript.
  - A request for the return of the Zuni war gods from the Brooklyn Museum, 1990 September 28; VHS videocassette (Cassette 3)
  - GIS Language System, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 4)
  - Zuni Settlement Act, 1990 February 09; VHS videocassette (Cassette 5)
  - A strand in the web, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 6)
    Directed by Valerie Weaver (professional name Madeleine Muir).
  - Duck Valley: harvest of hope, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 7-8)
    KAID-TV, Boise, Idaho
  - Next year country, 1982 January 08; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 9)
  - That awesome space, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 10-11)
    Produced by the Institute of the American West.
  - Future of agriculture in the Rocky Mountains, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 12-13)
  - Western songs, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 14-15)
    Northern Rockies Folk Festival series on KBGL-TV
  - Women performing folk songs, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 16)
  - Traditional songs, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 17)
  - Southern folk songs, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 18)
  - Duck Valley, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 19)
    Broadcast master
- Phonograph records
  - Soy Mexicano: traditional Mexican-American music from Southern Idaho, undated; Phonograph record (Disc 1)
    Side A:
    Hasta Garras
    Dejenme Llorar
    Nampa
    Corrido de Santos Hernandez
    Hace un Ano
    Rio Rebelde
    Las Gaviotas
    Side B:
    Flor del Campo
    Palomito Orgulloso
    El Becerro
    Cruz de Olvido
    Soy Mexicano
    Cien Ovejas
- Addendum, 2002
  - False promises: the lost land of the Wenatchi, 2001; VHS videocassetste (Cassette 1)
    A film by Rustin Thompson narrated by Jackie O'Ryan. Story based on historical research by E. Richard Hart. Running time 56:40.
  - False promises: the lost land of the Wenatchi (short version), 2001; VHS videocassette (Cassette 2)
    Running time 13:30.
  - False promises: the lost land of the Wenatchi (soundtrack), 2001; Compact disc (Disc 3)
    All compositions copyright of Salamander Music.
  - E. Richard Hart interview with Laura Lee Northcott, 2003 November 08; Audiocassette (Cassette 4)
    Hart discusses his book Pedro Pino: Governor of Zuni Pueblo 1830-1878. Broadcast on KVLR-FM, Twisp, Washington.